We've been running code that simply executes every line one by one from the top down.
Many times however, we want to run code only if a particular condition holds.
To demonstrate this concept,
let's take a look at this billing system for a pay-as-you-go mobile phone.
Say a customer has a credit balance for
their phone which they can use for calls and messages.
The customer can then set up a link to their bank account so that
if their phone credit balance goes below a threshold amount,
in this case five dollars,
then 10 more dollars of credit are added and their bank balance is build.
Here is a simple way of representing this billing system in code.
If the phone balance is below five,
add 10 to phone balance and subtract 10 from bank balance.
This is an example of an if statement.
An if statement is a conditional statement that runs or
skips code based on whether a condition is true or false.
In an if statement, the if keyword is followed by the condition to be checked,
in this case, phone balanced less than five,
and then a colon.
The condition is specified in
a Boolean expression that evaluates to either true or false.
After this line is an indented block of code to be executed if the condition is true.
So in this case,
these lines will only execute if it is true that phone balance is less than five.
If phone balance is five,
this condition evaluates to true and these indented lines of code are executed.
You can observe these changes in the output.
If phone balance is eight however,
this condition evaluates to false and these lines are not executed.
As you see in the output,
there were no changes to phone or bank balance,
which is what we expect to happen since the condition in this if statement was false.